Mary Bachman Papers
Mary Bachman Papers
1985-2018
Bachman, Mary.
1.0 linear ft.
Files, correspondence, research notes, and other material relating to the American comb collector. Includes photocopies of material dating back to the late 19th and early 20th century.
5390599
Biographical History
Mary Bachman is a member of the Antique Comb Collectors Club and editor of their newsletter. The club was formed as the Antique Comb Collectors Club (ACCC or AC3), and later became the Antique Comb Collectors Club International (ACCCI). She is also the author of Collector's Guide to Hair Combs: Identification and Values (1998).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mary Bachman Papers contains Antique Comb Collectors Club material, correspondence, photographs, printed material, subject files, and videorecordings.
The Antique Comb Collectors Club material conains address lists, communications with members and the Board of Directors, issues of the club newsletter (a few in hard copy, with a complete set on CD), club documents and publicity, and so on.
Correspondence contains general correspondene with other collectors and a small amount with sellers.
Photographs consists primarily of photographs of other collectors' combs. Many are labeled on the back.
Printed material contains clippings by and about Bachman and other comb collectors, including Jen Cruse and Belva Green, as well as pieces on combs and comb collecting generally.
Subject files were undifferentiated when received, and have been sorted by topic. Most of these have to do with various materials used in comb-making and manufacture, including horn, ivory, jet, and plastics.
Videorecordings contains "How to make a celluloid comb" and a VHS tape of a European television program.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by name or topic. Within each folder, where appropriate, items are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
See also the
Mary Bachman Antique Comb Collection
. has several other collections related to hair combs, as well as a considerable amount of material related to plastics history and production generally. Please to locate other collections related to plastics and industrial design, and refer to to locate cataloged publications. Please also visit the Plastics Collection Website.
Subject and Genre Headings
Plastics; Bachman, Mary.; Beall, Glenn.; Cruse, Jen.; Green, Belva.; Miller, Betty, 1933-; Antique Comb Collectors Club (U.S.); Antique Comb Collectors Club International.; Hair ornaments -- Collectors and collecting.; Ornamental combs -- Collectors and collecting.; Ornamental combs -- Societies and clubs.; Bibliographies.; CD-ROMs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; DVDs.; Newsletters.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Research notes.; Slides (photographs); VHS.; Video recordings.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary Bachman, 2019.
Inventory
- Antique Comb Collectors Club material
  - Address lists, 1985-1995; undated; office holders, members, various contacts (Box 1)
  - Board letters, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Conference material, 1993; 1999; one program, a few presentations (Box 1)
  - Constitution and history, 1999; history is by Betty Miller (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1985; 1996,; 2014; includes a few pages of "Generic Issue" (Box 1)
  - ACCCI newsletter archives, bachman_m_004; "from Brian Casey and Jo Sullivan"; PDF files; CD (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, open letters to members, budgets, publicity material, club information/brochures, etc. (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1994-2018; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ebay and other sellers, 2006 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Prints and color photocopies, includes large section noted as "Other members' combs" (Box 1)
  - Slides, possibly from a presentation? (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - About AC3, 1993-1997; undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings about/by Bachman, Mary, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Clippings about/by Cruse, Jen, 1997; 2000-2001,; 2007 (Box 1)
  - Clippings about/by Green, Belva, 1995; 1998,; 2001,; undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous, 1993-1995; 2003,; 2007,; undated (Box 1)
- Subject files
  This consists mostly of photocopies of books, book chapters, advertisements, catalogs, articles, and encyclopedia entries, some of which date back to the late 19th and early 20th century. There is also some printed material from websites, as well as unattributed typed notes and/or fragments of writings, some of which may have been drafts or portions of presentations or articles.
  - General, books, includes "Bibliography for Antique Comb Collectors Club" (Box 1)
  - General, museums (Box 1)
  - Amorosi, Samuel J., 1988; includes brief typed bio by unknown author (Box 1)
  - Art nouveau/art deco, includes photocopies of line art and pencil sketch comb designs (Box 1)
  - Celluloid and plastics (Box 1)
  - Hair styles, includes copy of article or presentation, "Combs and hair ornaments, or, (almost) anyone can wear a comb" by unknown author (Box 1)
  - Horn and tortoiseshell, includes copied pages from "The worshipful company of horners: A short history" by F.J. Fisher (1936) (Box 1)
  - Ivory, includes "Types of ivory" from a conference presentation, draft of article by Jen Cruse (Box 1)
  - Jet (Box 2)
  - Paste jewelry (Box 2)
  - Silver (Box 2)
  - Steel and iron, cut-steel and Berlin iron (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous manucripts, in most cases the author is not identified; topics include piqué, tips for dating and identifying combs, combs from India and Scandinavia, etc. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous printed items (photocopies), book chapter "The comb in human history," magazine story on collector Doris Langley Moore, still shots from Titanic (1997) of Rose holding/wearing her butterfly hair comb, article on Chinese hair ornaments, etc. (Box 2)
- Videorecordings
  - Des Gestes, un Objet le Peigne d'Ornement, 1997; note on label says "From European television"; bachman_m_001; VHS; running time 14:00 (Box 2)
  - How to Make a Celluloid Comb, bachman_m_003; DVD; running time 14:47 (Box 2)
  - How to Make a Celluloid Comb [audio only], bachman_m_002; DAT; running time 15:00 (Box 2)